ou know, biologically, I said- How much LSD should
you give an elephant?
(mellow music)
Well, to a reasonable person,
the correct answer is probably none.
But what if you needed to do
it for a scientific experiment?
In the 1960s, the CIA was working on
a top secret project known as MKUltra,
and one of their main
goals was to find out
how drugs like LSD could be
used to change human behavior.
And this is where elephants come in
because elephants are
normally quite docile,
but sometimes they just snap.
And the hypothesis was
that this change in
behavior might be triggered
by the release of an LSD-like substance
that naturally occurs in their brains.
So if that's true, then administering LSD
to a docile elephant might
reproduce that behavior.
So the real question was
how much LSD should you give
an elephant so that the
dose is large enough
to cause a psychological reaction,
but not so large that it causes harm?
(mellow music)
Well, the researchers didn't
know, LSD had never been given
to an animal that big,
but they did know that
the safe dose in cats
was around 0.3 milligrams.
Now, since an elephant has around
a thousand times the mass of a cat,
they figured we'll give it
a thousand times the dose.
They received approval to
perform the experiment on Tusko,
an Indian elephant at the
Lincoln Park Zoo in Oklahoma.
And there they injected him
with nearly 300 milligrams of LSD.
But within five minutes,
Tusko trumpeted, collapsed,
fell heavily onto his
right side, defecated,
and went into status epilepticus.
They administered a few other drugs
in an attempt to revive him,
but Tusko died shortly thereafter.
The mistake they made was to assume
that safe drug dosage
scales linearly with mass.
It does not.
And it turns out there are
a lot of things like this
that don't scale in the way you'd expect.
(mellow music)
For example, take the
smallest mammal by mass,
the Etruscan shrew,
and the largest land mammal,
the African bush elephant.
Which do you think has more heartbeats
over the course of its entire life?
Well, an African elephant has
around a billion
heartbeats in its lifetime,
and an Etruscan shrew also has a billion
heartbeats in its lifetime.
What about a wallaby?
Also a billion.
A two-toed sloth?
A billion again.
Just about every mammal, no matter
what environment they live
in, how large they are,
or even whether they live
for one year or 100 years,
they all get around a billion heartbeats
between the day they're
born and the day they die.
- Why a billion?
Why not a million?
Why not a thousand?
It's not these other numbers.
- That is every mammal except one.
This video is in large
part based on the book
Scale by Geoffrey West.
If you want to learn more,
I'll put a link to it
down in the description.
What's even more curious is that
just by knowing a mammal's mass,
you can predict a staggering number
of biological traits from its pulse rate
and reproductive output
to its total lifespan.
The same pattern holds for cities.
If you know the population and location,
that allows you to forecast
everything from average wages
and patent filings to crime
rates, disease prevalence,
and even the literal speed
at which pedestrians walk.
So how is that possible?
Well, for that, we have
to go back to the case
of Tusko the Elephant.
Researchers assumed that safe drug dosage
is proportional to mass.
Double the mass, double the dose.
But it turns out that the
speed at which an animal
can process chemical compounds
doesn't depend directly on its mass.
It depends more on its metabolic rate.
That is the number of calories it uses
in a given amount of time.
- There's a lot going on in your body.
Your heart is pumping, that takes energy.
You're moving food around.
Digestion takes energy.
Keeping your brain going
takes energy, breathing.
Everything that you do requires energy.
(mellow music)
- [Host] For a cat, for a single day,
they require roughly 250
kilocalories of energy,
used by all of their trillions of cells.
But there is nothing
special about a cat's cells.
If you take a cat's cells
and an elephant's cells
and put them under a microscope,
you'll find they're a
similar size, similar makeup,
and they perform the
same sorts of functions.
The same is true for other animals.
In other words, the building blocks
of animals are always roughly the same.
So an elephant that has
a thousand times the mass
has about a thousand times as many cells.
So you'd expect it would need a thousand
times as much energy.
So 250,000 kilocalories per day.
But that is where you run into problems.
- So what's the issue here?
If I'm an organism
and I'm burning up energy all day long,
that energy is radiated out
in the form of body heat.
So we're constantly losing
heat through our surface,
through our skin, to the environment.
- To see why this matters,
let's simplify the problem
and do the standard physicist thing.
Let's assume our animals
are perfect spheres.
To be clear, this isn't necessary
for the argument to work,
but it does make everything
a lot easier to follow.
Since the volume of an animal
is proportional to its mass,
our 3000 kilogram elephant
has a volume a thousand times
greater than our three kilogram cat.
So its radius must be 10 times larger.
That's because volume is
proportional to radius cubed.
But surface area only
grows as radius squared.
So the elephant's surface area
only increases by a factor of 100.
Generating a thousand times as much heat
while only having a hundred
times the surface area
to radiate it away would end very
poorly for the elephant.
If this were the case,
it would boil alive.
(mellow music)
So in 1838,
French scientists proposed
a different scaling law.
Since metabolism generates heat
and that heat is radiated
through the surface,
metabolic rate or B,
should scale in proportion
to the surface area, A, instead.
This became known as the surface law.
Now, we can rewrite this to see
how metabolic rate scales
as a function of mass.
Surface area is proportional
to radius squared,
so we can swap that in,
and if mass is proportional
to radius cubed,
then radius must be proportional
to mass to the one-third.
Plugging that in for R,
we find that metabolic rate should scale
with mass to the two-thirds.
- Really familiar example would
come from thinking about cooking.
(mellow music)
Maybe you want to make a
big turkey for Thanksgiving.
People commonly phrase it as
how long do I need per pound?
But that you realize is linear thinking.
The important thing is really
the thickness of the bird
or the roast, because
the heat is coming in
by conduction from the oven
and it's got to do thermal
diffusion into the meat.
The time for the diffusion will scale
like the characteristic length,
which in this case would be
the thickness of the meat.
It'll go like the dimension squared,
whereas volume of the meat is
going to be like length cubed,
and that's proportional to the weight
of the bird or the roast.
So when you put those things together,
you'll get that the characteristic
amount of time needed
to cook the roast will go like its mass
to the two-thirds power.
- So if I'm thinking about cooking a roast
that weighs twice as much as
another roast, how much longer?
Is that two to the two-thirds the time?
- Yeah, if you wanted
to double the weight,
then you only have to
cook it about 60% longer,
not 100% longer.
- [Host] Similarly,
according to this scaling,
an elephant that's a thousand
times as heavy as a cat
should only burn a hundred
times as many calories.
So 25,000 instead of 250,000.
And the appropriate dose of LSD for Tusko
would've been just 30 milligrams.
These two wildly different
predictions come from different
assumptions about how metabolic rate
scales as a function of mass.
But notice in both cases,
it's just proportional
to mass raised to some power.
These kinds of relationships
are called power laws
and all power laws have
a special property.
If you take the logarithm
of the X and Y values,
you get a straight line.
And the slope of the line is equal
to the exponent of the power law.
This makes it easy to identify
different types of power laws.
If the slope is one, that's
just everyday linear scaling.
If it's less than one,
like the surface law,
that is called sublinear scaling.
And if it's larger than one,
that is known as superlinear scaling.
For nearly a hundred years,
biologists generally agreed
that the two-thirds exponent
of the surface law was the
correct one for metabolic rate.
But then in 1932, Swiss
biologist, Max Kleiber,
decided to put it to the test.
He took the metabolic rates
of different animals from
a small dove at 150 grams
to a large steer at 680,000 grams,
and then he plotted
them against their mass
on a log log plot.
And as expected, all the data
did fall on a straight line.
But the slope wasn't two-thirds.
Instead, it was about three quarters.
This became known as Kleiber's Law.
It implies that if you
double an animal's mass,
metabolic rate goes up by about 1.68,
an increase of 68% instead of the 59%,
which would be predicted by
the two-thirds scaling law.
So according to Kleiber's Law,
an elephant burns roughly 178 times
as many calories as a cat,
or about 45,000 kilocalories.
And the actual LSD dose
Tusko should have received
was 53 milligrams, which is
around a sixth of the dose
the researchers gave him.
So that explains the dosing catastrophe
with Tusko The Elephant.
(mellow music)
Kleiber's original work was
based on a small data set,
primarily made up of mammals.
But if you plot the data for
a larger range of mammals,
as well as for other animals
like birds, reptiles, and fish,
you find that they all follow
roughly the same scaling relationship.
Now, they don't all fit
perfectly onto the same line
because the base metabolic rate
for warm-blooded animals is higher
than for cold-blooded ones,
but they all scale according
to the same power law,
mass raised to the three-quarters.
Some argue that this relationship
expands all the way down
to single cells and the molecular
machines inside of them.
If that's true, Kleiber's Law governs life
spanning more than 25 orders of magnitude.
But then the question is,
if an elephant has so many more cells
and each cell is a similar size
to a cell in a smaller creature,
and yet it's using
proportionately less energy,
like it's got a lower
metabolic rate per pound
or per kilo or per cell,
that's really saying that those cells
are functioning with much less energy.
- It's like there's some
efficiency to being big,
and it's hard to understand why.
What is it that the cells
are providing to each other,
somehow cooperating in some way?
- I just put in my calculator
100 to the three quarters,
so if you got an organism
that's 100 times bigger,
then according to this, only 31.6
times the metabolic rate.
So it seems like a big savings.
- It's a massive improvement, right?
It's a big savings.
It's a biological fact,
but people have been
arguing now for a century
what accounts for this three quarters.
(mellow music)
- In the decades following
Kleiber's observation,
the mystery only deepened.
Researchers discovered that
brain size also roughly scales
as mass to the three quarters,
and so does an animal's growth rate
and the amount of blood pumped per minute.
But not every property scales
as mass to the three quarters.
- If you ask how long a
creature will live, a mammal,
that tends to be proportional to its mass
to the one quarter power.
One over four, not three over four.
- [Host] So that means if you
double the mass of a mammal,
then on average, its lifespan
is around 19% longer.
Similarly, blood
circulation time also scales
as roughly mass to the one
quarter, while breathing rate
and heart rate both scaled
to the negative one quarter.
They're not all three quarters power laws,
but they are all multiples of a quarter.
So the question on everyone's mind was
where are these quarter power
scaling laws coming from?
- One popular theory emerged in the 1990s.
(mellow music)
Brian Enquist was studying
for an undergraduate degree in biology.
- Most of the biology
classes then that you take,
you learn about the Krebs Cycle
and then you have to memorize
all the different parts
of a flower and then all...
They have a different
terminology for everything.
- [Henry] But then one day
he took a zoology class
where they showed him those
quarter power scaling plots.
- [Brian] I just couldn't believe it.
I was like, "You got to be kidding me."
You know, this is kind of
like something fundamental
that's kind of like underlying
biological diversity.
And there I knew immediately that I wanted
to kind of quit my specialized
kind of plant physiology research
and do something associated with scaling.
(mellow music)
- [Henry] So Enquist started
studying for his PhD,
under Professor James Brown,
who had been thinking about
scaling laws for years.
So they knew that often
when power laws appear,
there's some form of self-similarity
in the underlying system.
So they wondered, what could
that self-similarity be?
And they suspected that it
might have something to do
with the way resources are
transported through the body,
specifically the networks that do this.
They had the biological intuition,
but to get a complete theory,
they needed a formal
mathematical framework.
In other words, they
needed a mathematician
or a theoretical physicist.
- And at the time, Jim was associated
with the Santa Fe Institute,
and he started asking around with,
is there anyone up here
that's interested in these
biological scaling relationships?
And then the president at the
time said, "You know what?
I know of this physicist
who's up at Los Alamos
who was talking about biological
scaling relationships."
And so we met Geoffrey and
it was like immediately,
it's like we'd been talking
about the same things
for like years.
It's like, you know, finding,
someone who's been like
speaking your language,
but no one could understand you.
- [Henry] So West, Brown
and Enquist teamed up
to try and find a compelling
explanation for Kleiber's Law.
- They started by assuming
three simple premises.
The first premise is that the networks
that distribute resources
are space-filling,
since they need to reach
every cell in the body.
The second premise is
that the terminal units
of those networks, the thinnest segments
on the outer periphery
of the delivery system,
have the same width regardless
of the size of the organism.
That is the outermost blood
vessels that carry nutrients
to an elephant's skin
cells are about as thick
as the ones in a mouse.
The elephant just has many more of them.
And the third premise is that over time,
evolution has driven
these transport networks
toward an efficient design.
So what should such a network look like?
(mellow music)
Well, intuitively, to get
fuel from one place to another
as efficiently as possible,
you want the path to be
as short as possible.
So basically a straight line.
But because fuel needs to
reach every part of the body,
you would also need many different paths.
And as you go to larger
and larger organisms,
the networks inside need to
reach a larger and larger volume.
One way to do this is
to stretch all the paths
and match the growth of the animal.
In this case, the volume of the animal
should scale as these
internal path lengths cubed.
Or if we rearrange that,
internal path length should scale
as volume to the one-third,
just like the overall
length of the animal does.
But this design is incredibly wasteful.
Take these two regions.
The two vessels that
are bringing blood here
go through almost the
same path in the body,
and they only split up just
before they reach their destinations.
If instead we had just one
vessel up to this point
and split it only when the
paths needed to diverge,
we could serve the two regions
using a lot less vessel material
and a lot less blood to fill the vessels.
Of course, you can extend this logic
for all the blood vessels in the body,
and you end up with a
much more efficient design
of branching blood vessels.
But now we run into another issue
because each branching point
provides an opportunity
for some of the blood to
bounce back, that is reflect.
If you have many reflections,
that would mean it
costs significantly more
energy to pump blood around.
So next, they argue that
nature should favor structures
that minimize reflections.
And as it turns out, this happens
if the cross-sectional area of the vessels
stays the same before
and after the branching.
So if you've got a cross-sectional area
of two centimeters squared
for the main vessel,
then each of the two
branches need to have an area
of one centimeter squared each,
for large vessels at least.
For smaller ones, daughter
branches can be a bit thicker
to allow blood to slow down
and exchange resources with
the tissue it's reaching.
If you keep repeating this
pattern across the network,
you end up with this, a
branching self-similar fractal.
And if you look at the actual shape
of the circulatory system,
it has this geometry.
So it seemed like they
were onto something.
- But how do you get from this
to quarter power scaling laws?
Well, mathematician Felix
Hausdorff discovered
that self-similar fractals
have an interesting property.
(mellow music)
Take a straight line segment.
It's completely one-dimensional
and not a fractal at all.
Hausdorff assigned this
line segment a value of 1.0.
But now imagine adding a few bends
and more bends to those bends.
If you keep doing this,
the line becomes more
and more fractal-like.
Eventually, if you keep applying
the right kind of contortions,
that one-dimensional line segment fills up
an entire region of the 2D plane.
Hausdorff assigned these
space-filling fractal curves
a value of 2.0, corresponding
to their dimensionality.
The same ideas apply to a 2D surface.
- So think about a piece of paper, right?
Two-dimensional.
All then the fractal network
is doing is crumpling up
that sheet of paper,
and it effectively fills
a ball of volume.
So you can now describe
that sheet of paper
as a sphere instead of a
two-dimensional sheet of paper.
- [Henry] Repeat the
right pattern of folds
at smaller and smaller
scales, and a 2D surface
fills more and more of a 3D volume.
In the mathematical limit,
it becomes space filling
with Hausdorff dimension of 3.0.
- [Brian] You know, biologically, I said,
"Well, what does that mean?"
That enables an organism for a given size
to pack in more of these
metabolic surface areas
than would be expected.
And it's because of this
fractal-like structure
that enables you then to pack
in and have all of these folds
and convolutions and on top of each other
to pack in an enormous
amount of membrane surfaces.
- As a result, the Hausdorff
dimension of the surface
of the circulatory
system is roughly three,
meaning its surface area doesn't scale
as its length squared,
but it's length cubed.
And since the metabolic rate hinges on
how fast resources can be
exchanged across the surface area,
well, it must also
scale like length cubed.
But remember, West, Brown and Enquist
wanted to explain Kleiber's Law.
So they needed to know how
metabolic rate scales with mass.
(mellow music)
Since every cell needs to
be served by the network,
this means that the volume
around the network should be proportional
to the animal's mass.
And since volume is just
surface area times length
and surface area is
proportional to length cubed,
that means both volume and mass
must be proportional to
length to the fourth,
which can be rewritten to show
that length is proportional
to mass raised to the one quarter.
And if you plug that into the equation
for the metabolic rate,
you find that the metabolic rate
must be proportional to
mass to the three-quarters,
exactly as Max Kleiber had found.
West, Brown and Enquist
published their work in 1997,
and it soon came to be known
as WBE Theory, after their initials.
- And the theory is quite rigid.
It makes very specific predictions.
This is good science.
Okay?
This is sticking your neck out,
and it's an incredibly beautiful theory.
(mellow music)
- [Derek] Take a look at this table
from Geoffrey West's book.
These are the scaling
exponents WBE theory predicts,
including many that are
not multiples of a quarter,
but all follow from the same theory.
For example, the radius
of an animal's aorta
should scale with its mass
to the three-eighths or .375.
And the area of its lungs
should scale with mass
to the 11-12ths or about 0.92.
In total, this chart makes
26 different predictions.
Now, these are the observed data.
Radius of the aorta, 0.36.
Lung area, 0.95.
- [Steven] That's the really shocking thing
about what they did.
They had a table with
something like, I don't know,
20 or 30 predictions of exotic exponents,
and that's what you
really see in the data.
So this one theory accounts not only
for the three-quarters
power of metabolism,
but for literally dozens of other things
that biologists have measured.
- Some of the scaling
laws are easy to explain
once you've got the
three-quarters law for metabolism.
Take a mammal's heart rate, for instance.
Heart rate is equal to the blood flow rate
over the amount or volume
of blood in every beat.
(mellow music)
The volume of blood
per beat has been found
to scale in direct proportion
to an animal's mass.
So that's just M.
And the blood flow rate?
Well, remember that
metabolism is all about
how nutrients get
distributed around the body.
So most biologists agree metabolic rate
and blood flow rate are directly
proportional to one another.
So heart rate should scale
as metabolic rate over mass.
Swapping in the scaling
law Kleiber had found,
that gives us M to the minus one quarter,
meaning bigger animals should have slower
heartbeats than smaller ones.
And this is exactly what
we observe in nature.
The world's smallest
mammal, the Etruscan Shrew,
has an extraordinary heart
rate of 1200 beats per minute.
That's 20 beats per second.
Whereas the biggest land mammal,
the African bush elephant,
has a typical heart rate of
only 30 beats per minute.
And we can do something
similar for lifespan.
One of the leading theories is
that an animal's lifespan is based on
the accumulation of metabolic damage.
That is, as each chunk
of tissue in an organism
processes nutrients over time,
this causes damage to accumulate,
and that over time
causes the animal to die.
So the rate at which an
animal accumulates damage
is its metabolic rate per unit of mass,
and its lifespan should be
the inverse of that rate.
If damage accumulates
faster, it dies sooner.
If it accumulates slower, it lives longer.
So lifespan is proportional to M over B,
or substituting in Kleiber's
Law, M to the one quarter.
So lifespan should increase with mass.
And you do see this in nature.
(mellow music)
A shrew only lives for one
to two years in the wild
while a mighty African elephant
can live up to 70 years.
So if you're a small mammal,
you have many heartbeats per minute,
but you live a relatively short life.
Conversely, if you're a larger mammal,
your heart beats much slower
and you live a lot longer.
- So it's the, you know,
live fast and burnout
and die young, right?
Or spend it frugally and
live a really long life.
- But you might have also
noticed something else.
Heart rate scales as B over M.
So it equals B over M times some constant.
And lifespan scales as M over B.
They're inverses of each other.
They scale in equal and
opposite directions.
Now, the total number of
heartbeats in an animal's life
is just the heart rate
multiplied by the lifespan.
So when you multiply these
two terms, they cancel out,
leaving you with just a constant.
So that suggests that no matter
what mammal you're talking about,
it should have roughly the
same number of heartbeats.
You can find that number by
just plugging in some examples.
Let's start with the Etruscan Shrew.
The shrew's 1200 beats per
minute multiplied by a lifespan
of around 1.5 years gives you
around 950 million heartbeats
in the course of the shrew's life.
Meanwhile, an African
elephant's 30 beats per minute
multiplied by a lifespan
of around 65 years
gives you a little over
a billion heartbeats.
And we could keep going.
(upbeat music)
But for nearly every mammal you look at,
you keep landing at the same figure of
around a billion heartbeats.
This is why nearly every
mammal from a tiny field mouse
to a gazelle, from a
cheetah to a hippopotamus,
they all get around a billion heartbeats
between the day they're
born and the day they die.
But there is one major outlier, one mammal
that gets significantly more
than a billion heartbeats.
And that is us, humans.
(mellow music)
We are the lucky ones.
Three centuries ago,
humans were much closer
to the standard value of
one billion heartbeats.
But around the mid 1800s, germ theory
and better sanitation
methods became widespread,
causing a stark decrease in
the number of child mortalities
and deaths from disease.
So life expectancy began to climb up.
And with it, the average number
of heartbeats in a lifetime.
If you look closely, you can
also see some significant drops
like this 1918 dip from
the Spanish flu pandemic
or over here, what appears to be
the impact of the Second World War.
But overall, the trend is clear.
We have systematically
been increasing the number
of heartbeats we get in
our lifetime to the point
where now the average human
gets nearly three billion
heartbeats before they die.
I don't know if there's a
better argument for science
and technology than this.
It has literally given the average human
more than a full extra life.
And it's not just humans.
Other mammals have been observed
to have much longer lives in
captivity when they're away
from the hazards they would
naturally encounter in the wild.
Or if you look at it purely
from the number of years we get,
we now have the lifespan
of a much larger mammal,
somewhere between an elephant and a whale.
But there is one curious
thing about this trend.
(mellow music)
Take a look at this graph.
It looks surprisingly similar
to the graph from before.
In fact, if you overlay them,
they look remarkably similar.
Now I want you to take a
guess at what this graph is.
Have you got your answer?
It is the number of
people living in cities.
For these two charts,
we're using data from parts
of the United Kingdom
where the record keeping
goes back several centuries,
but the rest of the world
has followed similar trends.
Of course, that doesn't mean
cities cause people to live longer,
but it goes against the
perception of cities
as being full of pollution and
breeding grounds for disease.
Already in 1889, a medical doctor wrote,
"The poisonous germs and
pollutions of the city,
it's impure air and water, bad sewage,
and endless nuisances."
So how do you reconcile these two views?
Or more specifically, is
there any quantitative data
on how smaller cities
compare to larger ones?
- It turns out this is something
that Geoffrey West pursued
after his work with Brown and Enquist.
He and collaborators like
Luis Bettencourt and others
have looked at scaling laws in cities.
(mellow music)
- [Host] They looked at
how different properties
like the amount of crime scale
as the population of the city increases,
and what they found is that if you plot
serious crimes on a log log plot,
the data clusters around a straight line
with a slope of 1.15,
meaning crime grows faster
than linear or super linear.
So for every doubling
of a city's population,
you get around 2.2 times
as many criminal cases
or around 120% more crime
as opposed to the 100%
you might naively expect.
To make matters worse, researchers found
that the same general pattern
holds for the amount of wastewater
and even the number of AIDS cases.
The exact exponents vary a little,
but overall, as cities grow larger,
you systematically get more of each.
So it seems like that medical
doctor was onto something.
And you might think life on
earth would be better off
if we all lived in small towns instead,
but that might not be the case.
(mellow music)
In 2006, Dirk Helbing, Christian Kuhnert,
and Geoffrey West looked at how the number
of gas stations scales as
a function of population.
- If a city is twice as
big, does it need twice
as many gas stations?
Because, you know, we have to
supply not exactly nutrients,
but energy, gas, for all those cars.
- [Host] The naive expectation is that
if you double the number of cars,
you're going to need to
double the amount of fuel,
so double the gas stations.
To find out whether this was true,
they plotted the data on a log log plot
and found a straight line.
But the exponent wasn't
one, it was about 0.8.
This means that for every
doubling, you only need around 74%
more gas stations, which
is a decent savings.
(mellow music)
The amount of roads and electrical cables
also scale in roughly the same way.
The rough figure that
West gives in his book
is that they all have scaling
exponents of around 0.85.
- It is interesting
that some of the things
that we can share, like you can drive
on the road, but so can I.
When it's shared resources, yes,
cities can be surprisingly green.
The argument is that
cities can be even greener
than you might think than living out
in the middle of nowhere.
- But cities have even bigger benefits.
Things like total wages, GDP,
and the number of patents
all scale superlinearly,
with exponents that cluster
somewhere around 1.15,
meaning that for every doubling in size,
you get around 120% more of each.
All of this becomes especially significant
when you compare a small
town of say 50,000 people
to a city 100 times its size
because infrastructure needs
only need to go up by a factor
of about 50 while total wages,
GDP, patents and inventions,
they all go up by a factor of 200.
Unfortunately, disease
and crime also go up
by the same factor.
Or look at it this way,
on a per person basis,
you'd only need about
half the infrastructure,
while you get double all
the socioeconomic factors.
So cities far from being
detrimental to the world,
they might actually be
one of our best inventions
and an indirect driver
of a lot of scientific
and technological progress.
Perhaps this is also why people often say
that life in the city feels faster.
A feeling that seems justified
because researchers looked at
how fast people walk in
cities of different sizes.
And they found that
people literally do walk
faster in larger cities.
- That turns out to depend on city size.
It's not just that the
sidewalks are congested or not.
It's just like the vibe
gets people amped up.
They move faster in cities.
- So the pace of life
seems to be increasing,
but that may come at a cost
because as one person put it,
"everything nowadays is ultra.
Everything is being
transcended continually
in thought as well as in action.
No one knows himself any longer.
Young people are stirred
up much too early in life
and then carried away in
the world of the times.
Wealth and rapidity are
what the world admires".
Could it be that life
is accelerating so fast
that humans won't be able to keep up?
Well, probably not
because this quote was written in 1825
by Wolfgang von Goethe.
For the past 200 years
and probably longer,
almost every generation has
felt like life was accelerating.
And yet every generation has managed.
So I think it's likely we can continue
to adapt indefinitely.
And as cities continue to grow in size,
all of us will continue
to reap the benefit
of economies of scale in much the same way
that mammals benefit from being larger.
But while WBE Theory seems to predict
where the exponents in
biological scaling laws come from,
for cities, there is no widely accepted
explanatory theory yet.
Trying to explain where
those exponents of 0.85
and 1.15 come from is one of
the big goals for theorists.
Although even WBE Theory is
not universally accepted.
For one, the fact it
predicts the right exponents
doesn't necessarily mean the
theory itself is correct.
There are a few other
theories that predict
some of the same scaling exponents,
and there are also some other critiques.
- There's a lot of discussion.
It may look convincing.
And personally, I tend to
think it is very impressive.
But I have very good
colleagues like Peter Dodds
at University of Vermont,
and he thinks that a
lot of the data analysis
is either not done exactly right
or that the data are so noisy
that you shouldn't really
take this so seriously.
- Dodds even argues that Kleiber's Law
itself might not be true.
(mellow music)
- In the 1960s, there's a
symposium on energy metabolism,
some name like this in animals,
and at the end of it, they vote 29 to zero
that it's going to be
three quarters, right?
Because, you know, you
got to set some rules.
If you go back and look at the data,
which no one is really
doing anymore, right,
the data does not work.
Like it doesn't work.
(mellow music)
- [Henry] This is a
graph of metabolic rate
as a function of mass based on a study
that looked at 391 species of mammals,
much larger than Kleiber's range.
And it looks like the three-quarter
slope fits quite well.
But this is just the
top part of the chart,
the biggest mammals.
If you zoom out, you see that
the rest of the mammals appear
to fall on a line that's
closer to two-thirds.
And in recent studies of bird metabolism,
you also find a slope that appears closer
to two-thirds than three-quarters.
Could it be that those French scientists
from centuries ago were right,
that metabolic rate really does
just scale with surface area?
Well, not so fast.
(mellow music)
For one, many recent studies
of cold-blooded animals find slopes
that are significantly
higher than two-thirds.
The bigger problem is that measuring
metabolic rates is difficult.
It generally involves putting
animals in a container
and taking very precise measurements
of their heat production
or oxygen consumption,
all while ensuring that the
animal is in an unstressed,
low activity resting state.
Unsurprisingly, this is
particularly difficult
to pull off with large animals.
And as a result, many studies
have found scaling exponents
where the error bars include both
two-thirds and three-quarters.
Today, the research community is split.
Many uphold Kleiber's Law and
the three-quarter scaling,
while others think it's two-thirds.
But a growing number suspect
that there is no
universal scaling exponent
across all of life.
In fact, it may very well be the case
that the metabolic rate of larger mammals
scales as their mass
to the three-quarters,
while for smaller ones, it's
their mass to the two-thirds.
- You know, it's like
everything in science
that there are people
arguing, and that's good.
- I guess the bigger exhortation
would be someone to really measure it,
measure things beautifully.
You know, we're in 2026,
has to be not just one
elephant at one zoo,
it needs to be measured again really well.
- [Host] What everyone does agree on
is that scaling laws are real.
- Life is not linear all the time.
There are deals to be had.
There's often in real life
departures from proportionality,
and you have to be aware of it.
Sometimes things punch above their weight,
and as you get bigger,
you get more efficient.
Sometimes there are detriments to size.
- So it pays to know how things scale.
Clearly from an energy
efficiency perspective,
animals benefit from being larger.
Similarly, all of us potentially stand
to gain from having more
people living in larger cities.
It could lead to more
discoveries and inventions,
and in doing so, improve
the standard of living
for all of us, which
might even give us more
heartbeats in our lifetimes.
From the surface law to
Kleiber's law to WBE theory,
how metabolic rate scales with mass
has been one of biology's
biggest debates for centuries.
By collecting better data
and analyzing it carefully,
there's a good chance
that the next generation of
researchers could be the ones
to finally put this debate to rest.
It could be one of you watching
or a student that you know.
And today's sponsor, Brilliant, is helping
to train the next
generation of researchers,
preparing their minds to solve the huge
questions they'll face.
Brilliant is a cutting edge personal tutor
that helps any student excel
in math, science, and coding.
When it comes to learning,
one-on-one tutoring really
is the gold standard,
but this can be expensive
and logistically difficult.
As a substitute, students
often turn to AI for guidance.
But most AI platforms hinder learning
by simply just giving away the answers.
So instead, Brilliant is
designed to guide students
to their own aha moments
by asking probing questions
and by breaking problems
down step by step.
For instance, check out what
happened when I launched one
of Brilliant's lessons
on rotating coordinates
and told its tutoring tool
that I was struggling.
It asked me a specific follow-up question
and even labeled relevant
points on the graph
to give me a nudge.
Brilliant is an excellent
aid for the young math
and science learners in your life.
It's the kind of tool I wish
I had when I was in school.
So click the link below
or scan the QR code
to get started with
Brilliant's tutor for free,
or upgrade to premium
to unlock all courses.
And right now, Veritasium
viewers can save 20% off
an annual subscription at
brilliant.org/veritasium.
So I want to thank Brilliant
for sponsoring this video,
and I want to thank you for watching.